Inventory of the Truman H. Kuhn papers, 1918-1989
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Truman H. Kuhn papers
1918-1989
Kuhn, Truman H.
00799
4.95 cubic ft. (11 document boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The Truman H. Kuhn papers include biographical material, administrative files (many from foreign university projects), geology articles, books, newspaper clippings, correspondence, maps, notes, mining reports, speeches, and subject files. The material traces his academic career, both as a student and a professor, and his professional career including his work at the Los Angeles County Flood Control District, and his consulting work for foreign universities in Saudi Arabia, Turkey, and Indonesia.
Biography of Truman H. Kuhn
Truman H. Kuhn spent most of his professional life as a professor of Geological Engineering at the Colorado School of Mines in Golden, Colorado. He was born in 1908 in Glendora, California. He graduated from Citrus Union High School in 1922 and earned a B.S. degree from the California Institute of Technology in 1930. He graduated with a Ph.D. from the University of Arizona in 1940. From 1930 to 1937 he was an engineer geologist for the Los Angeles Flood Control District, and from 1940 to 1942 he worked for the Magma Copper Company as a geologist. He was also a consulting geologist for the Eagle-Picher Mining and Smelting Company and for the Arizona Molybdenum Corporation.
Mr. Kuhn became an Assistant Professor of Geology at the Colorado School of Mines in 1942, and he was promoted over the next 12 years until he achieved the rank of Faculty Dean and then Vice President for Administrative Affairs. He held many active positions outside of the School of Mines, including Geological Consultant to the School of Mines Research Foundation and Registered Professional Engineer in Colorado. He was a consultant to Saudi Arabia, Turkey, Indonesia, and other foreign governments as an expert on setting up mining and petroleum colleges. He also had an abiding interest in the problems involved in maintaining academic and professional standards in geology and geology education. He belonged to many boards concerned with these issues including the Colorado State Board for the Registration of Engineers, the American Institute of Professional Geologists, and the ECPD Engineering Education and Accreditation Committee.
He wrote numerous articles and produced 16 publications on mining geology, applied geology, engineering education, and manpower. He also received numerous awards including the medallion of merit from the University of Arizona, the Tasker H. Bliss medal as a military engineer, and the George R. Brown medal from the Colorado School of Mines. Truman Kuhn died on November 14, 1988.
Scope and Content
The Truman H. Kuhn collection includes biographical material, administrative files (mostly foreign projects), geology articles, books, clippings, correspondence, maps, notes (academic), mining reports, speeches, Colorado School of Mines subject files, and five geology books.
The material traces the academic and professional career of Kuhn from the days when he was an Engineer Geologist for the Los Angeles County Flood Control District in the late 1930s to until after his retirement from the Colorado School of Mines in the 1970s. His administrative files contain material related to his work as a consultant to Saudi Arabia, Turkey, and Indonesia in helping them to establish colleges of mining and petroleum. The articles, books, maps, reports, and speeches reflect that he was an active geologist who wrote manuscripts and made speech/presentations related to geological matters. His notes, subject files, and geology books reflect his work as a student and academician at the University of Arizona and the Colorado School of Mines.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no other known archival collections created by Truman H. Kuhn at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The Truman H. Kuhn papers, 1918-1989, were given to the American Heritage Center by Edith Kuhn in 1989. The papers were received in good condition and partial order.
Access Terms
Colorado School of Mines.; Geology--Study and teaching.; Mining schools and education.; Mining corporations.;; Colorado--Geology.; Wyoming--Geology.; Arizona--Geology.;; Engineering geologists.; Geology teachers.
Education; Colleges and Universities; Agriculture and Natural Resources; Mines and Mineral Resources; Science
Container List
- Biographical, 1938-1974; Series I.; (4 Folders)
  Focusing on employment and honors. Arranged alphabetically by type.
  - Truman H. Kuhn, Employment Applications, Clippings, 1938-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colorado School of Mines – Interim Executive Officer, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - University of Montana, President – Job Offer, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Civil Service, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Administrative Files, 1941-1980; Series II.; (2.5 document boxes; 15 folders)
  Projects arranged alphabetically.
  - Arizona, Copper Creek, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - College Accreditation, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Indonesia, CEPU, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Indonesia, Java, CEPU, (AKAMIGAS), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Istanbul Technical University, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Libya – Report by George T. Bator, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Malaysia, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New Mexico, Apache Creek, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Saudi Arabia, University of Petroleum and Minerals, 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folders 3-4)
  - Turkey (ATIF Dinar Istanbul), 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Turkey, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folders 1-2)
  - Zambia, 1965-1966, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folders 3-4)
- Articles and Books, 1938-1964; Series III.; (12 folders)
  Publications written by Kuhn. Arranged alphabetically by publisher and topic.
  - American Mineralogist, “A New Occurrence of Dioptase in Arizona,", 1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Daily Journal, “Engineering in Evolution”, “Colorado School of Mines, One of World’s Largest…,”, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Economic Geology, “Pipe Deposits of the Copper Creek Area, Arizona,", 1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mines Magazine, “Mining Engineering in 1963,”, December 1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mines Magazine, “Mining Geology and the Colorado School of Mines,”, March 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mines Magazine, “Professional Education and Practical Training,”, July 1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scientific Manpower (NSF), “Engineering and Science – A Struggle for Survival,”, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - University of Arizona Bulletin, “Bunker Hill District” – Arizona Zinc and Lead Deposits, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - University of Arizona Bulletin, “Childs Aldwinkle Mine – Copper Creek” – Some Arizona Ore Deposits, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Colorado School of Mines (Book), Applied Geology, A Symposium, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Metal Mining Board (Book), “Colorado Vanadium,”, November 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - University of Arizona Bulletin (Book), “Geology and Ore Deposits of the Superior Mining Area, Arizona,”, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - Professional, Social, 1947-1989; Series IV.; (3 folders)
  Arranged by date.
  - Professional, Social, 1947-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, Humor, Minor Awards, 1947-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, Ute Indians, Sand Roses, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Maps, 1918-1962; Series V.; (3 folders)
  Arranged alphabetically by area.
  - Colorado – Golden, Denver, Colo. School of Mines, (Map Segments), 1938-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Turkey, India, 1940-1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - United States – Arizona, Utah, North Dakota, 1918-1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Notes, 1930-1952; Series VI.; (1.5 document boxes; 11 folders)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Geological – Pipes, Mining Districts (Arizona), (1 of 2), 1938 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Geological – Deposits, Formations (2 of 2), 1938 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Geology – Chemical Tests, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Geology 203 (Crystallography), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Geology – Economic Geology, circa 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Geology 421-102-310 (Exams), 1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Geology 423 (Exams), 1942-1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Geology 432 (Exams), 1952 (Box 5, Folders 5-6)
  - Geology – Mineralography, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Geology Student, Kuhn - Non-Metals, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Geology Student, Kuhn – Optical Mineralogy, December 1930 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Geology Student, Kuhn – Ore Deposits I, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Geology Student, Kuhn – Ore Deposits II, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Geology Student, Kuhn – Ore Deposits III, 1937-1938 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Photographs, circa 1940s; Series VII.; (2 folders)
  Portraits and snapshots of Kuhn and his wife.
  - Truman Kuhn (Professional Portraits), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Kuhn (Snapshots), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Reports, 1931-1977; Series VIII.; (3 document boxes)
  Written by Kuhn. Arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1931-1977; Subseries 1.
    - Coal Study – Colorado School of Mines, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Coal Study – Colorado School of Mines Research Foundation, “Texas Gulf Sulphur,”, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Engineers Council for Professional Development – Accreditation of Engineering Programs, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Gas Resource Studies, …Recoverable…Gas in the United States, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Los Angeles County Flood Control District, San Gabriel Dam No. 2 – Geology, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Los Angeles County Flood Control District, San Gabriel Dam No. 1 – Geology, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Los Angeles County Flood Control District, San Gabriel Dam No. 3 – Geology and District Progress Report, 1931, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Molybdenum – California, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Geology/Mining, 1931-1963; Subseries 2.
    - Bigger Mine, Jefferson County, Colorado, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Burke-Martin Mines, Summit County, Colorado, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Cherokee Mine, Larimer County, Colorado, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Claims-Moab, Utah, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Clear Creek County, Colorado, 1948-1955 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Coal Fields, Colorado and Wyoming, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Congress Mine, Yavapai, Arizona, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Conquerer Mine, Empire, Colorado, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Criterion Mining, Park County, Colorado, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Dauntless Tunnel and Lateral, Park County, Colorado, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Essex Claim, Gilpin County, Colorado, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Golden Earth, Encampment, Wyoming, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Great Eastern Mining, San Juan County, Colorado, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Grizzley, Clear Creek County, Colorado, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Hardscrabble Mining District, Custer County, Colorado, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Hoosier Claim, Hinsdale, Colorado, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - International Vanadium, Gila County, Arizona, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Iron Mountain, Laramie Range, Wyoming, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Leader - Copper World Mines, Pima County, Arizona (1 of 2), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Leader - Copper World Mines, San Xavier/Pima County, Arizona (2 of 2), 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Magma-Apex, Pinal County, Arizona, 1942-1957 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Paymaster Mine, Summit County, Colorado, October 1951 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Pride of the West Mine, Silverton, CO, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Sunnyside Coal, Carbon County, Utah, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - U. S. Army Underground Test Program in Utah and Colorado, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Ute Indian Data, Mesa County Colorado, 1942-1944 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Ute Indian Data, Gunnison County Colorado, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Veta Mad / Veta Glad Mines, San Juan County, Colorado, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Speeches and Presentations, 1938-1970; Series IX.; (1 document box)
  Written by Kuhn. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Accreditation of University Geology Departments, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - An Ideal Curriculum in Geology and Geophysics, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bert S. Butler, G.S.A. Cordilleran Section, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Childs-Aldwinkle Mine – Copper Creek, Arizona, 1938-1943 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Commencement – Kiowa Colorado, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Computing in Schools of Mineral Engineering, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Copper Creek and Mammoth Molybdenum Deposits of Arizona, Colorado Scientific Society, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Education and Mineral Engineering Manpower, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Educational Programs of AIME, ASEE Annual Meeting, June 1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Engineering and Science – A Struggle for Survival, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Impact of the School of Mines on the industrial Development of Colorado, Committee on Industrial Development, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Mining Engineering in 1963 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959-1968 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - The Patient Still Lives, Mining and Metallurgical Society of America, February 1961 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Professional Education and Practical Training: An Answer to a Dilemma, Colorado MBD Section of AIME, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Stanley Orville Reichert, 1912-1970 (Memorial) (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Visiting Professors Seminar, Continental Oil Company, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Subject Files, 1939-1983; Series X.; (1 document box)
  - Colorado School of Mines, 1939-1975; Subseries 1.
    - Advanced Examinations, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Articles, Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Centennial Celebration, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Centennial Planning, Handouts, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Mineral Deposits (Lecture), 1951 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Mineral Deposits (Outlines), 1956-1959 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Student Examinations (Blank), 1939-1950 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Petrology (Notes), undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Rock-Forming Minerals (Notes), undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - General, 1956-1983; Subseries 2.
    - Canada – Campana Ltd., Watrous Area, Saskatchewan, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Event - Forty Sixth Annual Engineers-Panel “Better Health for Engineers,”, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Event – Mountain States Telephone and Telegraph, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Mineral Separation Corporation, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Books, 1950-1976; Series XI.; (1 document box)
  - Biographies of the Members of the Mining and Metallurgical Society of America, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Crystallography by Paul H. Keating, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory Manual for Mineralogy by Stanley Reichert, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Modern Coastal Sedimentary Environments Alabama and Northwest Florida by Harry C. Kent, May 1976 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Prospector 63, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Prospector 66, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 6)